<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religion [and] loyalty inseperable. A sermon preached at the assizes held at Nottingham, September the 5th, 1690. By Clement Elis, M.A. Rector of Kirkby, in the county of Nottingham. Octob. 2. 1690 Imprimatur, Carolus Alston, R.P.D. Hen. Episc. Lond, à sacris.</title>
            <author>Ellis, Clement, 1630-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84378</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897317</idno>
  <idno type="VID">135236</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248509323</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231486</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897317</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99897317e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84378)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2483:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religion [and] loyalty inseperable. A sermon preached at the assizes held at Nottingham, September the 5th, 1690. By Clement Elis, M.A. Rector of Kirkby, in the county of Nottingham. Octob. 2. 1690 Imprimatur, Carolus Alston, R.P.D. Hen. Episc. Lond, à sacris.</title>
                  <author>Ellis, Clement, 1630-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for William Rogers, at the Sun, against St. Dunstan's Church in Fleet-street; and Clement Elis, bookseller in Mansfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135236:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135236:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion &amp; Loyalty</hi> INSEPERABLE.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES HELD AT Nottingham, <hi>September</hi> the 5th, 1690.</p>
            <p>By <hi>CLEMENT ELIS,</hi> M. A. Rector of <hi>Kirkby,</hi> in the County of <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license" subtype="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Octob. 2. 1690.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Carolus Alston, R. P. D. Hen<lb/> Episc. Lond. à Sacris.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun,</hi> against St. <hi>Dunstan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleet street;</hi> and <hi>Clement Elis,</hi> Bookseller in <hi>Mansfield.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135236:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135236:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFUL <hi>Richard Taylor,</hi> Esq HIGH-SHERIFF OF THE COUNTY OF Nottingham.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have ever been so sensible of my own manifold Weaknesses, that it was never easie to me to appear in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> on any of these more Solemn Occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And hence alone it was, as I hope you do believe, that You so hardly prevail'd with me to appear there at this <hi>Assizes.</hi> For tho' I was well satisfied, that the Work you invited me to, was a Work that ought to be
<pb facs="tcp:135236:3"/>done by some body; yet could I not think every one fit for so great a Task, and least of all such an one as I, whom long <hi>Privacy</hi> and <hi>Retirement</hi> has in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure unfitted for any <hi>Publick</hi> Employment; and especially at such a time as this, when the Distempers of Men are come to that height, that something more than ordinary should be found in that Man, who can hope that any thing which he can offer in order to a Cure, may prove either acceptable or effectual.</p>
            <p>But being no longer able to resist the Importunities you were pleas'd to use with me, and having first humbly applied myself to <hi>Almighty God</hi> for his Direction and Assistance; after some serious Thoughts, what <hi>Subject</hi> might be most proper for a Discourse in so <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Honourable</hi> an <hi>Assembly;</hi> considering both the little <hi>Fear of God</hi> which most Men seem to have before their eyes, and the <hi>uneasiness</hi> of many under so good a <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> as God hath now blessed us with, and their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Murmurings</hi> at our present Condition, by much too good for us; I could not think of any thing more suitable to our present state, than what is recommended to us in those Words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> which I have made choice of.</p>
            <p>How well I have performed, what (at your Request, Sir) I undertook, I must necessarily leave it to every one to judge as he shall see cause; and what the success will be. He only knows whose infinite Power over-rules the perverse Wills and unruly Affections of Men, and who after the planting of a <hi>Paul,</hi> and watering of an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos,</hi> must give the increase, or all that's done by Man is as good as nothing I can (I thank God) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort myself in this Testimony of my <hi>Conscience,</hi> That I have here deliver'd nothing, which I am not verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded
<pb facs="tcp:135236:3"/>is agreeable to the Will of God, and both seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and necessary to be taken notice of and conscientiously practised by us: and that my whole Design is only this, to perswade Men to the earnest pursuit of their <hi>own</hi> and their <hi>Country's Happiness,</hi> by <hi>leading quiet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Lives, in all godliness and honesty,</hi> under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Government. And I hope no Man can find a reason why he should be angry with me for this.</p>
            <p>Having thus done what I was able, in compliance with your desire, Sir, to serve <hi>God,</hi> our most <hi>gracious Princes</hi> whom his Goodness hath set over us, and my <hi>Country,</hi> seeing your bodily Indisposition would not allow you to be my Auditor, I could not reasonably deny you, requesting it, a Copy of my Sermon; but finding it to be in order to a Publication, I was at a stand, considering it could not be your own Judgment that moved you to it, you having at that time neither heard nor seen it. But when you told me it was the desire of those worthy <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen</hi> who were present; and when both the <hi>Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> and the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Aldermen</hi> of the Corporation of <hi>Nottingham</hi> had conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended to desire it of me: and when that <hi>Honourable Judge</hi> the <hi>Lord Chief Justice Pollexfen</hi> had not only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me by his Publick <hi>Approbation</hi> of what had in his Presence been delivered, but understanding that I had for hast omitted something of what I had prepared, was pleas'd to say, I should do well to publish it entirely as I had prepared it; I had no Power to refuse so general an Invitation, which it could no longer be called <hi>Modesty,</hi> but a most unreasonable as well as unmannerly and sullen <hi>Obstinacy</hi> to disobey.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135236:4"/>
            <p> To <hi>You</hi> therefore, Sir, and to all those <hi>worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen</hi> who were pleas'd to join with you in this Request, (which I ought to look upon as a Command) I do in all due humility and respect, present these my poor endeavours for the Glory of God, and the Publick Good: not doubting but your constant and exemplary Practice of those unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionable Duties which are therein, howsoever recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you, will make them much more serviceable to those great Ends, than otherwise they are like to be Neither shall I need to fear or regard the <hi>Censures</hi> this plain Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course may meet with from any others, so long as I have not only the <hi>Conscience</hi> of a most <hi>honest Design,</hi> but also the <hi>Judgments</hi> and <hi>Patronage</hi> of so many Judicious Persons, testified in their daily <hi>Exercise</hi> of both <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> even of all that I have here exhorted to, to guard me from them.</p>
            <p>That our blessed God may give us all Hearts so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardful of, and thankful for the great and wonderful Works which he hath wrought for us, as that the sence of his undeserved Goodness therein manifested to us, may be an everlasting Obligation upon us to his <hi>Fear,</hi> and the <hi>keeping of all his Commandments always, that so it may be well with us, and with our Children for ever:</hi> That we may all have Grace seriously and effectually to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the things that belong unto our Peace, before they be hid from our eyes:</hi> That we may no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperately expose ourselves, either to the <hi>Wrath</hi> of God by our <hi>Wickedness,</hi> or to the <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Scorn</hi> of our Enemies by our <hi>Discontents, Divisions,</hi> and mutual <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimosities.</hi> Lastly, That God may bless <hi>You,</hi> Sir, and all the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Magistracy</hi> with <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> in your <hi>Honourable</hi> Stations, and make you
<pb facs="tcp:135236:4"/>Illustrious <hi>Examples</hi> of all <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Goodness</hi> to your <hi>whole Country,</hi> and finally reward you with the <hi>Crown of Righteousness,</hi> is, and shall be the hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your very humble Servant,</hi>
                  <lb/> CLEMENT ELIS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:135236:5"/>
            <head>Advertisement</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LEast I should seem too careless of their Reputation who encouraged me to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish the following Discourse, I must desire the Reader to take Notice, that there are some parts of it which want their Approbation. These (that I might keep within my Hour) I omitted in the delivery of it, but now insert them here, as they stood in my Notes, distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished from the rest by this Note</hi> (').</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135236:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. XXIV. 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>My Son, fear thou the LORD and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to change.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>YOU hear the Words of a great King, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired Preacher, and the wisest of mortal Men. All this you know, was <hi>Solomon.</hi> But that's not all, you hear the Words of One infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely both greater, and wiser, and better than <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> even of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s King, and <hi>Our</hi> King, of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s God, and <hi>Our</hi> God; of that great God,
<note place="margin">Psal. 82.1.</note>
               <hi>who stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Congregation of the Mighty, and judgeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gods:</hi> Nay more,
<note place="margin">Psal. 76.12.</note>
               <hi>Who cutteth off the spirit of Princes, and is terrible to the Kings of the Earth?</hi> 'Tis He, I say, the All-wise God, by the wisest of Men, the Almighty God by a mighty King, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Father by the Father of his Country, at once commanding Duty, and teaching Wisdom; not that which is <hi>earthly, sensual, devilish,</hi> the Wisdom of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> without the Innocence of the <hi>Dove;</hi> which, through <hi>envying and strife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 3.15, 16, 17.</note>
               <hi>confusion and every evil work,</hi> hath made this World too like Hell; by making Men little better than Devils one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but that which <hi>descendeth from above, first pure in the fear of the LORD,</hi> then <hi>peaceable</hi> in <hi>the fear of the King:</hi> so making <hi>wise</hi> for the <hi>other</hi> World, and <hi>this</hi> too. This is the <hi>Wisdom</hi> which <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Solomon</hi> teacheth us in these words, <hi>My Son, fear thou the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135236:6"/>LORD and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein observe:
<list>
                  <item>I. The Words expressive of a <hi>Fatherly Affection</hi> in a <hi>great King, My Son.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. The Words containing and offering most <hi>wise</hi> and <hi>seasonable Advice</hi> to the <hi>Subject. Fear thou the LORD and the King: and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I must do no more but touch upon the former of these in my way to the latter, on the <hi>Fatherly Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> to lead me the more fairly to the <hi>Filial Duty</hi> of the <hi>Subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. The words expressive of a Fatherly Affection in a great King are these, <hi>My Son.</hi> So the <hi>Divine Wisdom</hi> taught this great <hi>King</hi> to salute his <hi>Subject.</hi> And thus will every <hi>King,</hi> whom God hath been pleas'd to bless with any considerable share of <hi>Solomon's Wisdom,</hi> even thô he should attain to all <hi>Solomon's Power</hi> too, account it no less his <hi>Wisdom</hi> than it is <hi>Duty,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean himself as a gracious <hi>Father</hi> towards his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> saith of himself,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.9, 10.</note>
               <q>That <hi>the Preacher was wise, and sought to find out,</hi> Verba desiderii, <hi>acceptable</hi> and pleasing <hi>words.</hi> Yet such as must be, <hi>Verba veritatis</hi> too, <hi>Words of Truth,</hi> and such were these.</q>
               <hi>Policy</hi> will teach a <hi>Tyrant</hi> to call <hi>Son,</hi> till he has made a <hi>Slave;</hi> but Divine <hi>Wisdom</hi> teacheth a good <hi>King,</hi> no lefs <hi>sincerely</hi> than <hi>charmingly</hi> to utter these acceptable words, <hi>My Son.</hi>
               <q>This is the condescending Language
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135236:6"/>of the great <hi>God</hi> to his poor Creature; and therefore well may it become the Mouth of the greatest <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> upon Earth to his Fellow-Creatures, as the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of his Subjects are.</q> Neither indeed shall <hi>Princes</hi> ever find out a surer way to make themselves <hi>Great,</hi> and their Subjects <hi>Good,</hi> than this of treating them as their Children.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> had <hi>Power</hi> given him of God to Govern his People; and so have all Kings: And <hi>Solomon</hi> had <hi>Wisdom</hi> too, given him of God, to Govern his <hi>Power,</hi> and so have not all. The Wisdom of God had taught him, how most firmly to hold the aweful Sword of a <hi>Majestick King,</hi> in the gentle hand of a <hi>tender Father:</hi> Who, thô he owe Correction, no less than Protection to such of his Children as need it; yet (as the great <hi>Father of Mercies</hi> doth) always chastiseth in <hi>Love.</hi> And then indeed will every wise King esteem himself highest in <hi>Royal Majesty,</hi> when in a truly <hi>Paternal Government</hi> he most nearly resembles the great King of all the World, from whom all his Authority is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived: Who,
<note place="margin">Psal. 33.5.</note> thô <hi>he loveth righteousness</hi> and <hi>is excellent in power, and in judgment, and in plenty of Justice: and Men do therefore fear him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 37.23.</note> Yet <hi>is the earth</hi> also <hi>full of his goodness;</hi> in the midst of Judgment he remembers Mercy, and seems most delighted to be known by that encouraging <hi>Name, The LORD GOD,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 34.6, 7.</note>
                  <hi>merciful and gracious, long suffering, and abundant in goodness and truth; keeping mercy for thousands, forgiving iniquity, and transgression, and sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was therefore a most silly Ambition, which <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> somewhere derides in some Heathen <hi>Princes,</hi> who loved to look upon their own Pictures drawn arm'd with <hi>Thunder</hi> and <hi>Lightning:</hi> ambitious to imitate that in God, which is most unimitable, his <hi>Power</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135236:7"/>
                  <hi>Greatness,</hi> and <hi>terrible Majesty:</hi> and no whit desirous to do it in that wherein they might both most honour <hi>Him,</hi> and magnifie <hi>themselves</hi> before the World, his <hi>Fatherly Goodness.</hi> For then indeed are <hi>Princes</hi> truly <hi>Soveraign,</hi> then are they arrived at the most <hi>Absolute Power,</hi> when they over-awe their Subjects more by that right <hi>Royal Prerogative</hi> of a <hi>Paternal Goodness,</hi> than by all their <hi>Laws.</hi> Thus they become <hi>Inthron'd</hi> in the very <hi>Hearts,</hi> and command the <hi>Affections</hi> of their People; and so may assure themselves both of their <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Purses</hi> too, whenever they shall need them.</p>
               <p>Next therefore to that most glorious One of <hi>DEFENDERS OF THE FAITH, Princes</hi> should glory in no Title more, than in that very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient One of <hi>PATRES PATRIAE, Fathers of their Country;</hi> and indeed that other, <hi>Defenders of the Faith,</hi> when well considered, seems not another, but the very same, so long ago entail'd by God himself on all right Christian Princes, <hi>Nursing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isai. 49.23. Senec. in Med.</note>
                  <hi>and nursing Mothers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regnare diu nemo potest, qui timetur tantùm:</hi> said the <hi>Tragaedian</hi> well, <hi>He that's only fear'd cannot hope for a long Reign. Let them hate, so they fear,</hi> might be the word of a <hi>Tyrant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. in Herc.</note> as unwise as cruel, <hi>Cui omnis in ferro est salus:</hi> Farewel to his Safety, whenever his Sword breaks. <hi>Let them love, that for love they may fear:</hi> will ever be the word of a good and wise Prince.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And so it will be also of every wise and good <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi> who will never value his <hi>Authority</hi> on any other account, than that of having more power and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to do abundance of good in the World. And this he will be best able to do, when Men reverence him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135236:7"/>more for his <hi>Goodness</hi> than for their <hi>Greatness.</hi> As therefore his first care is, that all may learn both <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> in his <hi>exemplary</hi> Life; so his next will be to sweeten the most necessary severity of a <hi>Judge,</hi> or <hi>Justiciar,</hi> with the meekness and compassion of a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and when Justice commands him to punish, his Fatherly behaviour will always shew,
<note place="margin">Isai. 28.21.</note> That as <hi>Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> is God's <hi>strange work,</hi> so is it his also, and that's like God, <hi>He afflicteth not willingly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3.33.</note>
               <hi>neither grieveth the children of men.</hi> I must say no more here of this Point, 'tis enough to have noted, as by the way, that the Language of <hi>wise King Solomon</hi> to his <hi>Subject,</hi> was not, <hi>My Slave,</hi> or <hi>my Vassal,</hi> but, <hi>My Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The following Words are they wherein we are principally concern'd, which contain and offer unto us most wise, and now, if ever, seasonable <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Solomon</hi> here gives in Three Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Fear thou the LORD.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Fear thou also the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>And,</hi> that thou may'st not be drawn away from the fear of either, <hi>Meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>The fear of the LORD,</hi> is a very ordinary Phrase of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> importing no less than <hi>All Religion,</hi> or the whole Duty of Man to God. And it would be very needless to prove, That <hi>the fear of the King,</hi> here jointly, and in one word commanded with <hi>the fear of the LORD,</hi> implies <hi>All Loyalty,</hi> or the whole Duty of Man again to his <hi>Prince,</hi> or <hi>Civil Governour.</hi> A true and awful sence of the <hi>Excellency, Majesty, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity,</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the Person, is that Root in us,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135236:8"/>whence all our Acts of <hi>Honour, Subjection, Resignation</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> do naturally spring forth. Well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore said the <hi>Psalmist,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 36.1.</note>
               <hi>The transgression of the wicked saith within my heart, that there is no fear of God before his eyes.</hi> No fear of God, and then be sure of Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression in abundance. And his Advice is always ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry necessary,
<note place="margin">Psal. 4.4.</note>
               <hi>Stand in awe, and sin not.</hi> Whoso stands not in awe will be always sinning.</p>
            <p>First then, <hi>Fear the LORD,</hi> but then <hi>fear the King</hi> also. Will you have it the words of our blessed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note>
               <hi>Render to</hi> Caesar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caesar<hi>'s, and unto</hi> God <hi>the things that are</hi> God<hi>'s.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de Idolol. c. 15.</note>
               <hi>That is,</hi> saith <hi>Tertullian, the Image of</hi> Caesar <hi>on the Money to</hi> Caesar, <hi>and the Image of God in the Man to God; thy Money to</hi> Caesar, <hi>thy self to</hi> God. Fear God as <hi>God,</hi> so as thou canst fear none but God. Fear <hi>Caesar</hi> as a <hi>Man,</hi> yet (as the same Father saith) <hi>as the Man next to God.</hi> To the unquestionable <hi>Soveraign Authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apolog. c. 30. Ad scap. c. 2.</note> and <hi>Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Power</hi> of the <hi>Almighty One,</hi> there can no less be due than the most <hi>Absolute Subjection;</hi> to that <hi>Will</hi> of his which is the Universal <hi>Law,</hi> and can never be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Just,</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> it must be our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to yield an Obedience without reserve. But to all the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> on Earth, how high soever they be, seeing there be higher than they, and they no more but the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the <hi>Supreme</hi> in Heaven, we owe indeed a <hi>Conscientious</hi> Obedience <hi>for the LORD's sake,</hi> yet under this Restriction, <hi>In the LORD only,</hi> always <hi>limited</hi> by the Laws of God. In short, Fear the <hi>LORD</hi> as much as you <hi>can,</hi> fear the <hi>King</hi> as much as you may.</p>
            <p>And then that you be not drawn away from the fear of either,
<note place="margin">Vid. Poli Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nops. in Loc.</note>
               <hi>Meddle not with them that are given to change:</hi> Mix not, have no dealing with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135236:8"/>
               <hi>Vulgar</hi> reads it <hi>Detractors,</hi> the <hi>Chaldee</hi> and <hi>Syriack, Fools;</hi> the <hi>Septuagint</hi> and <hi>Arabick</hi> thus renders it, <hi>Disobey,</hi> or <hi>Oppose neither of them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esther 1.7.3.8.</note> In the <hi>first</hi> and <hi>third</hi> Chapters of <hi>Esther,</hi> and elsewhere our <hi>English</hi> renders the word, <hi>Diverse from;</hi> and so I shall make bold to take it here, for Men <hi>diverse</hi> from those who fear both God and the King, and of the same unhappy temper with that <hi>unjust Judge</hi> in the Parable,
<note place="margin">Luke 18.4.</note> who <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feared God, nor regarded Man.</hi> And to bring this home to our <hi>Translation,</hi> these, we may be sure of it, are always the <hi>Changers,</hi> the <hi>Restless,</hi> or <hi>Tumultuous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iterantibus. Ar. Mont. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellibus Pisca. Rerum nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum studiosis. Ver. Tegu. Variantibus, discere panti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, seditiosis, Mercer.</note> as some read it; who are very uneasie, and long to be shifting, when-ever they live under any thing that has the face of <hi>good Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To speak distinctly, <hi>first</hi> of the fear of the LORD, and <hi>next</hi> of the fear of the <hi>King;</hi> that is, of our whole Duty to both; and then to shew the manifold mischie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous consequents of medling with Men of a contrary temper, is not to be made the business of an hour. Give me leave therefore to confine myself to this one Observation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fear of the LORD, and the fear of the King, or sincere Religion, and true Loyalty, are Things inseperable.</hi> Where the one is, both are; where both are not, there is neither. What therefore God in his Command hath join'd together, let no Man in his Practice pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to put asunder.</p>
            <p>To demonstrate which Truth, <hi>That sincere Religion, and true Loyalty are Things inseperable,</hi> it will be enough for me to make good these two Things.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That there is no</hi> sincere Religion <hi>in him that is not</hi> truly Loyal.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That there is no</hi> true Loyalty <hi>in him that is not</hi> sincerely Religious.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:135236:9"/>
            <p> And both these I do not doubt but, by the help of God, at this time to make very clear to every consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Christian. And I hope, this being a work so sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, considering the Age we live in, it will not be thought altogether improper in this so Publick and Venerable Assembly.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>There is no</hi> sincere Religion <hi>in him that is not</hi> truly Loyal. This I am consident you will very readily grant me, considering only these three very obvious Truths, which our very Christianity obligeth us to believe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That God is the Absolute Soveraign Monarch of the whole World.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the same Soveraign Power doth actually di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spose of all the Kingdoms of the Earth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That he hath strictly commanded Subjection to those unto whom he so disposeth of them.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Certainly I may presume, that no Man will have the face to appear this day in such an Assembly of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians as this, and not own the Divine Authority of the Holy Scripture, and supposing but this, a very few words will here be enough to clear these Truths.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God is the Absolute Soveraign Monarch of the whole World.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psalm 24.1.50.12.89.11.97, 1.99.1.103.19.</note> Of this the Holy Scripture is full, <hi>The earth is the LORD's,</hi> (saith <hi>David) and the fulness thereof, the World, and they that dwell therein. The LORD reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, let the Earth rejoice.</hi> And again, <hi>The LORD reigmeth, let the People tremble. The LORD hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared his Throne in the Heavens, and his Kingdom ruleth over all.</hi> If this be so, then the most entire Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction must needs be acknowledged due unto him, and that, not only in a ready Universal Obedience to all his <hi>Commands,</hi> but also in a most cheerful submission to all his wise <hi>Dispensations.</hi> A <hi>total</hi> and <hi>unreserved Resigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135236:9"/>of <hi>our</hi> Wills to <hi>God</hi>'s Will, whether it be of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi> or of <hi>Providence,</hi> being the <hi>Natural Allegiance</hi> every one of us owes unto his <hi>Divine Majesty</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, <hi>The same Soveraign Power doth actually dispose of all the Kingdoms of the earth.</hi> Hear the Holy Scripture again,
<note place="margin">2 Kin. 19.15.</note>
               <hi>He is the God of all the Kingdoms of the earth,</hi> and <hi>he alone.</hi> His Right and Title are unquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; because, as it follows, <hi>He hath made heaven and earth.</hi> Nor is this only a Dormant Right, which he doth not actually exercise, for,
<note place="margin">Dan. 4.17.</note>
               <hi>The most High ruleth in the Kingdom of Men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will.</hi> 'Tis <hi>He that changes the times and the seasons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2.21.</note>
               <hi>and</hi> (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be the means or instruments he is pleased to make use of) 'tis <hi>he that removeth Kings, and setteth up Kings.</hi> And this he doth (saith <hi>Origen) Non per Arbitrium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Homil. 4. in Lib. Judicum.</note> not by his <hi>Prerogative</hi> only, in a meer <hi>Arbitrary</hi> way; but <hi>Pro ut merita nostra deposcunt,</hi> in a <hi>Judiciary</hi> way, answerably to the behaviour of a People, as a righteous <hi>Judge;</hi> so the <hi>Psalmist, God himself is the</hi> Judge,
<note place="margin">Psal. 75.7.</note>
               <hi>who putteth down one, and setteth up another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note>
               <hi>There is</hi> then you see, <hi>no Power but of God, the Powers that be are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd of God.</hi> And in all the great Revolutions of Kingdoms and States, we ought to have our eyes prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally fix'd upon the <hi>Spirit in the Wheels.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 1.20, 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Lastly, There are not many Duties more plainly commanded, more cogently press'd, or more frequently inculcated, than the Duty of <hi>Subjection</hi> to them unto whom God so disposeth of Kingdoms.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. Tit. 3.1. 1 Tim. 2.2.</note>
               <hi>Every Soul must be subject,</hi> and that, <hi>to every ordinance of man.</hi> We must <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>obey their Commands, Pray for their Persons, Honour them, Pay them Tribute and Custom,</hi> and all this, <hi>for the LORD's,</hi> and <hi>for Conscience-sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whoso grants all this, as every <hi>Christian</hi> must do, must needs grant withal, that every Pretence to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135236:10"/>Religion, in him that yields not a <hi>Legal Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Civil Government</hi> under which he lives, so far as it may be consistent with that Obedience which he owes in the first place to the Laws of God, whom he is always to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey rather than Man, (and this is all we mean by <hi>true Loyalty</hi>) is one of the vainest things in the World. And therefore I take the first Proposition to be undeniably proved.</p>
            <p>And here it might be thought as proper to my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as it is at this day seasonable, were not my <hi>Abilities</hi> as much as my <hi>Time</hi> too short for such a Task, to offer something by way of Answer to those <hi>Questions</hi> about <hi>Legal</hi> TITLES, NON-RESISTANCE, and PASSIVE-OBEDIENCE, which have been so very troublesome of late to many, as to render the Doctrine now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd in a great measure impracticable to them; so that they cannot pay either so cheerfully or so compleatly as they ought to do, their ALLEGIANCE to those <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Princes,</hi> whom it hath pleased the <hi>Divine Goodness</hi> by a most <hi>miraculous Providence</hi> to advance unto the Government of these Kingdoms. But instead of this, as I know it to be enough, so I hope it will not be thought too much for me in this place, humbly to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a little Advice, as one that desires to be found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and I dare with some confidence promise myself, that it will be thought by all here very <hi>Christian</hi> and <hi>seasonable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me then <hi>first</hi> more <hi>generally,</hi> advise all Men, who think themselves concern'd to have a clear Resolution of these and the like <hi>Questions,</hi> before they dare own the Powers under which they live, to be very cautious how they venture to disobey the plainest <hi>Commands</hi> of God, or to disregard the most remarkable <hi>Dispensations</hi> of his <hi>Providence,</hi> meerly in complaisance to some, at
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135236:10"/>best, disputable <hi>Principles</hi> of their own, which they have been taught, it may be <hi>unawares,</hi> only by <hi>Custome</hi> and <hi>Education,</hi> to be too unreasonably fond on. <q>And this Advice may, I hope, take the better with some of them who now seem most to need it, because it is the very same they have so often given to the <hi>Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in another Case.</q> More <hi>particularly:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. On the one side, all they who are so <hi>scrupulous,</hi> as that they dare own no <hi>Allegiance</hi> due to any <hi>Prince,</hi> so long as they can invent any thing to say against the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality</hi> of his <hi>Title,</hi> are highly concern'd to be well as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured of this one thing, that God's Command of <hi>Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Higher Powers,</hi> makes it not his Duty to be subject, unto whom his <hi>Prince's Title</hi> is not first clear'd beyond all dispute. And he that can be assured of this, will, I fear, be forced to grant, what I would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, for Government's sake, and for God's too, hear granted, that this Command was given in vain, to very great Numbers of them who most need it. However there are not a few things which must be very well consider'd, before such an assurance can be had. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What kind of Legal Titles those <hi>Powers</hi> then had, unto whom our blessed <hi>Jesus,</hi> and his <hi>holy Apostles</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded those first Christians, and more especially the <hi>Jewish Converts,</hi> for <hi>Conscience sake</hi> to be <hi>subject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. How St. <hi>Paul</hi> could, consistently with their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, even in the most general terms, enjoin Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to what he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Present Powers,</hi> or (seeing some will rather have it so) the <hi>True Ones,</hi> even to all, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in any degree of Eminence; and yet not give us the least hint of our Duty to examine, or of any marks whereby we might trie their <hi>Titles,</hi> and so save ourselves from a sinful Obedience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What <hi>Right</hi> God hath given to any <hi>People</hi> having
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135236:11"/>made Government their Duty, to provide themselves of good <hi>Government</hi> when 'tis wanting; or to secure to themselves, as well as they may, the <hi>ends</hi> and <hi>benefits</hi> of good Government; or, whether God have made it their Duty to quit all this, in complement to what some please to call a <hi>Legal Title.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. What setled Government there is ever like to be in a Nation, wherein all Men will not soon, I fear, come to be of one mind, if every one may deny <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>present Governour,</hi> so long as he hath any scruple in his head, about his <hi>Title</hi> to the Government.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Where God himself doth not, as in <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> immediately interpose, and by some positive Law fix the <hi>Constitution,</hi> design the <hi>Person,</hi> and intail the <hi>Right,</hi> what it is in every <hi>Nation</hi> that makes a <hi>good Title,</hi> and who they be that must determine, <hi>What it is, Who hath it, Whether</hi> and <hi>by What it</hi> may be <hi>lost,</hi> or <hi>forfeited,</hi> whenever such Disputes as these arise about it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Lastly, by what means <hi>Conscience</hi> may possibly escape the <hi>Snare</hi> thus laid, and enjoy the freedom of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the plain Commands of God, without being continually on the rack of <hi>Doubts</hi> about <hi>Titles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho, I say, I may not for my weakness presume to determine in these matters, yet must it needs be of highest concernment to them who refuse <hi>Allegiance,</hi> because of <hi>disputable Titles,</hi> for their own satisfaction to have them well determined. All I shall at present farther advise them to, is only this, That thô they seem to me over <hi>scrupulous</hi> already in one point, they would yet be a little more <hi>cautious</hi> in <hi>another;</hi> I mean, least the Dust they raise about the <hi>Titles</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> do not blind them so, as that they cannot discern the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which he challengeth to himself,
<note place="margin">Jer. 27.5, 6.</note>
               <hi>To give all the Lands to whom it seemeth meet unto Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:135236:11"/>
            <p> Thus saith God of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 26.20.</note>
               <hi>I have given him the land of Egypt for his labour, wherewith he served a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, because they wrought for me, saith the LORD.</hi> Since then it hath pleased God to send us in our greatest need, not a <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>bloody Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> but a most <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>gracious Prince;</hi> not a <hi>Stranger</hi> to our <hi>Nation,</hi> but a <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Royal Family;</hi> to <hi>labour,</hi> and that in a very hazardous Service, not <hi>against</hi> us, but <hi>for</hi> us: seeing this <hi>most excellent Prince</hi> hath so visibly <hi>wrought for God,</hi> not, as that other, in a way of <hi>Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> but of <hi>Salvation;</hi> not <hi>eventually</hi> only, but <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally</hi> also; seeing that God hath wrought even <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculously</hi> for <hi>Him,</hi> and for <hi>us</hi> by him; and seeing he hath by such a continued <hi>Train</hi> and <hi>Series</hi> of <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Providences,</hi> all visibly tending to the Glory of his own <hi>Goodness,</hi> in the securing of the <hi>Protestant Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest,</hi> and the Safety of <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> professing his <hi>Holy Truth,</hi> so clearly in all appearance determin'd the matter to our hands: If we stand yet disputing <hi>Titles,</hi> when we should <hi>be praising the LORD for his Goodness, and declaring the Wonders that he doth for the Children of Men:</hi> We have all the reason in the World to fear, least by a questioning a <hi>Right</hi> which God hath so sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally own'd, we provoke him to assert his <hi>own Right</hi> to our sorrow, <hi>By taking away a good King in his wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 26 17.</note> and <hi>setting them that hate us to Reign over us;</hi> as once he threatned a murmuring Generation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And now in the next place, on the other side, I must needs say, That a little more Christian <hi>Modesty</hi> and <hi>Caution</hi> too, might very well become those very bold and over-daring People, who, I doubt, as <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderately</hi> as <hi>confidently,</hi> in the most general terms, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Non-Resistance;</hi> and declaim (as to me it seems) with no less <hi>indiscretion</hi> than <hi>virulence,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135236:12"/>against what they blush not to call the <hi>Nonsence</hi> of <hi>Passive-Obedience.</hi> My Advice to these Men is, That they would <hi>first</hi> seriously bethink themselves, what it may be within them, that thus transports them beyond all bounds of Christian <hi>Sobriety,</hi> yea, and all that <hi>regard</hi> to which is due (I say not to the <hi>present</hi> only, but) to <hi>all Government.</hi> And then beware, I beseech you <hi>Sirs,</hi> least aiming, it may be, very blindly, at the <hi>Church of England,</hi> you chance to hit both <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppose we, that these <hi>Doctrines</hi> may have possibly been <hi>unwarily</hi> over stretch'd and misapplied by some, and more <hi>maliciously</hi> wrested and abused by others, to serve very ill ends and purposes: It may be, I might truly say, that there is no part of the <hi>Gospel of Christ,</hi> which hath not by some been thus abused; and yet I hope you will not turn <hi>Apostates</hi> because of that. Truly I must believe these <hi>Doctrines</hi> to be <hi>sound</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> so long as I can believe the <hi>Gospel,</hi> which so plainly teacheth them to be <hi>Divine Truth.</hi> And well I think it too for the World, that they are so; otherwise, I can as little see how any <hi>Government</hi> can be maintained in it, as I think any one can shew me, Why the holy <hi>Jesus</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced him <hi>blessed that is persecuted for righteousness sake:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.10.</note>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.19.</note> or St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls it, <hi>Thankworthy, if a man for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science toward God, endure grief, suffering wrongfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let but <hi>them</hi> therefore in every <hi>Government,</hi> whose proper work it is, for I am sure 'tis not the <hi>Divine</hi>'s, lay open before Men the true <hi>Constitution</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> and say plainly, what are the <hi>Supreme Powers</hi> therein, as some such there must be, that so there may be no longer any danger of a mistake in the <hi>Application,</hi> and then I affirm, not only, that it is a <hi>Contradiction</hi> to say, the <hi>Supreme Power</hi> may be resisted, but the <hi>Government</hi> will soon become sensible how much it owes to <hi>Christ</hi> for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135236:12"/>delivering, and to the <hi>Church</hi> for maintaining this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and how ill they deserve of all Men, who <hi>ridicule</hi> it. I hope the <hi>Church of England</hi> will never prove so unfaithful, either to <hi>Christ</hi> or the <hi>Civil Government,</hi> as either to be <hi>droll'd</hi> or <hi>hector'd</hi> out of a <hi>Doctrine</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath so plainly taught her.</p>
            <p>And as to that <hi>late Case</hi> of ours, whence some have taken occasion to make all this Noise, I shall only say, That as I think it administred very little, if any cause at all for such unbeseeming Discourses: So I am very sure it made us all the cause in the World to be heartily thankful to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> who by an undeserved Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness was pleas'd so to order the whole Affair for us, as to prevent the greatest of <hi>Temptations;</hi> and to make us a fair way to escape, without being put (as many of our poor suffering Neighbors have been) to the Trial how we would have exemplified our Doctrine of a <hi>Passive,</hi> as we had done that of an <hi>Active</hi> Obedience, so far as it was lawful, and so our Duty.</p>
            <p>I may now, I hope,
<note place="margin">In Apologet. ad Scap. c. 1, 2.</note> close this part of my Discourse with those well-known words of <hi>Tertullian, We,</hi> saith he, <hi>in the Emperors admire and honour the Judgment of God, who hath set them over the Nations.</hi> And again, <hi>The Christian is no Man's Enemy, least of all the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's, whom he knowing to be set up by his own God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not choose but love, honour, reverence, and pray for his safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. I proceed now to the <hi>Second</hi> Proposition, <hi>There is no true Loyalty in him that is not sincerely Religious.</hi> He fears not the <hi>King</hi> as he should do, who fears not <hi>God.</hi> 'Tis only <hi>Conscience</hi> towards God that can make a Man truly <hi>Loyal</hi> to his Prince.</p>
            <p>And this Truth will become very clear, when these Four things are well considered.
<list>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:135236:13"/>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the Apostles lay the Foundation of</hi> Loyalty <hi>in</hi> Religion.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Mankind hath ever thought</hi> Religion <hi>the only sure Bond to</hi> Loyalty.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>All other Bonds but</hi> Religion <hi>appear too weak.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>All Obedience paid on any lower account is too little.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Apostles lay the Foundation of</hi> Loyalty <hi>in</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Hence perswading us to <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> they are so very careful at every turn to mind us of <hi>God, There is no Power but of</hi> God, <hi>the Powers that be, are ordained of</hi> God. <hi>He that resisteth the Power, resisteth the Ordinance of</hi> God:
<note place="margin">Psal. 82.</note>
               <hi>He is the Minister of</hi> God. Therefore hath God himself given to <hi>Magistrates</hi> the Name of <hi>Gods. We must needs be subject not only for wrath, but for</hi> Conscience <hi>sake, and submit for the LORD's sake. For so is the will of God,</hi> saith St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Mankind hath ever thought</hi> Religion <hi>the only sure Bond to</hi> Loyalty.</p>
            <p>Hence is it, that <hi>Governours,</hi> distrusting all other <hi>Obligations,</hi> have always thought an <hi>Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> their very best security.</p>
            <p>Hence the very <hi>Atheists</hi> will have <hi>Religion</hi> to be no more but a <hi>Politick Invention</hi> for the better upholding of <hi>Government;</hi> so tacitly confessing, how unwillingly soever, that <hi>Government</hi> cannot be upheld, but by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> And thereby justifying the greatest <hi>severity</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men of his temper, as the worst of Enemies to <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence <hi>lastly,</hi> the wisest of the Heathen <hi>Law-givers,</hi> to lay this only sure Obligation on the People, feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Laws to come from some or other of their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitious <hi>Deities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This sence Men have always had, that <hi>Government</hi> cannot stand if you take away <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:135236:13"/> 3. <hi>All other Bonds but</hi> Religion <hi>appear too weak,</hi> Men will as <hi>Sampson</hi> did his Cords, easily snap them all in sunder, whenever they have a mind to shake themselves and break loose. As <hi>Antigonus</hi> call'd the State of Kings a <hi>great Slavery,</hi> so without <hi>Religion</hi> in the People, will every <hi>King</hi> find himself one of the very <hi>meanest,</hi> that is, a <hi>Royal Slave,</hi> and his <hi>Scepter</hi> no more but a despica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Reed,</hi> which any one will find strength enough to break at his pleasure, and choose which he will do, bow the <hi>knee</hi> to him in mockery, or <hi>crucifie</hi> him in earnest.</p>
            <p>And yet, it may be, some who are not at all ashamed, that all the World should know they have no <hi>Religion,</hi> will be very angry that any one should suspect their <hi>Loyalty.</hi> Who can help it? I will say very fair, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, prove your <hi>Loyalty</hi> and take it; only remember by the way, that as there is a <hi>temporary Faith,</hi> so is there a <hi>temporary Loyalty</hi> also, which may help one for a-while to make a fine flourish with in the World, so long as it will serve his private ends; but in time of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will wither away, and that for want of <hi>Religion</hi> to take deep rooting in.</p>
            <p>It must be a very bad <hi>Government</hi> indeed, which it is no Man's Interest to uphold, and so long as one stands by the <hi>Government,</hi> tho' it be but to serve his own turn of it, he will be accounted <hi>Loyal.</hi> But then 'tis very plain, that he who endeavours to uphold the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> only because it upholds <hi>him,</hi> will for the same rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son be no longer a Friend to it, than he imagines it, whether truly or falsly, 'tis all a case, a Friend to him. Men will very hardly be brought by any thing but <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> to trade any longer on the Common Stock, when once they can hope to thrive better by setting up for themselves.</p>
            <p>Suppose it were true, which one seems to make the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135236:14"/>first Principle of his <hi>Politicks, That every Man is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally an Enemy to every Man:</hi> and then suppose too, as you must, That <hi>Civil Government</hi> is nothing else but a <hi>forced Combination</hi> of one pack of <hi>Enemies</hi> to strengthen themselves against another. Now seeing this <hi>enmity</hi> can never be extinguish'd by any thing but <hi>Religion,</hi> what should hinder it, without that, from breaking out into <hi>new Conspiracies</hi> within the bowels of the <hi>old one,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Selfishness</hi> can get Power, and a Sword strong and sharp enough to cut in pieces the <hi>first Combination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Man that has made his <hi>Estate</hi> his <hi>God,</hi> will even <hi>Idolize</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> too, whatever it be, for his <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s sake, so long as he finds sat <hi>Offerings</hi> daily coming in by it to his <hi>Idol.</hi> But let him be call'd upon to offer largely to the support of the <hi>Government,</hi> he will begin to <hi>curse</hi> by his God, what but now you thought he had <hi>worship'd;</hi> the thing is unmask'd, and what was a <hi>seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>Government,</hi> appears in truth a <hi>real Slavery</hi> to his <hi>Estate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Man of an <hi>aspiring Spirit</hi> will even fall as low as you will have him, so he can hope to rise the higher in the rebound. He will kiss the Hand of his <hi>Prince,</hi> or the <hi>Pope's</hi> Toe, all's a case, so long as he has hope to <hi>climb</hi> by the help of either. But if the <hi>Government</hi> will not find him a place high enough for his <hi>Ambition,</hi> this will quickly swell him, till he be too <hi>great</hi> to be <hi>govern'd.</hi> He was <hi>obedient</hi> only that he might stand as <hi>high,</hi> and as <hi>near</hi> the <hi>Throne of Majesty</hi> as he could, and he will venture a step or two too far, and sit down in it, if he can, rather than be content not to stand as near it as he would be.</p>
            <p>He whose <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> are grown too great to be any longer fed with the broken <hi>Off-falls</hi> of such an Estate as they have left him, may seem very <hi>Loyal,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:135236:14"/>whilst by all the vile Arts of <hi>Flattery</hi> and <hi>Obsequiousness</hi> he is labouring to insinuate himself through his <hi>Prince's Favour</hi> into his <hi>Coffers,</hi> and all his <hi>Loyalty</hi> is onely his <hi>Impatience</hi> to live <hi>soberly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some others there may be, who for want of some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else to cover their wickedness, are fain to use some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like <hi>Loyalty</hi> for a cloak, and to seek a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> either in a <hi>corrupt</hi> or <hi>necessitous Government,</hi> from the <hi>Penalties</hi> of good <hi>Laws. David</hi> once had a Guard of no very good Men: and a very good <hi>Prince</hi> may some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be driven to very hard shifts, and to call into his assistance one sort of bad Men, to guard him from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Yet is it not their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> nor any other good quality in them, but their <hi>obnoxiousness to the Laws</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that could perswade them to afford him their help. But whenever such a <hi>King</hi> shall recover his just liberty of acting as the <hi>Minister of God for the punishment of evil doers,</hi> these seeming <hi>Loyalists</hi> will shew themselves then just as faithful to him, as they are now to God and their own Souls. No wonder, if they who are always defying their <hi>God,</hi> and bidding him <hi>damn</hi> themselves, should not be shie in cursing their <hi>King,</hi> whenever his <hi>Justice</hi> provokes them. Neither can any good reason be given, why such Men should not be altogether as willing to venture upon Damnation for <hi>Rebellion,</hi> as for <hi>Prophaneness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Lastly, <hi>All Obedience paid on any lower account is too little,</hi> and deserves not the name of <hi>true Loyalty.</hi> Not to honour the <hi>Magistrate</hi> as the <hi>Minister of God,</hi> is to debase him in our esteem, and in our thoughts, to degrade him from that high State and Dignity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it hath pleased God to advance him.</p>
            <p>From what has been said, I think, I may now very safely conclude, <hi>That under good Government, to be a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135236:15"/>good Man and a good Subject are so much the same, that he who is the one is both, and he who is not both is neither.</hi> And this is it I undertook to shew.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine thus clear'd, I have but two things more to do at this time, and I most heartily beseech God to assist me with his Blessing.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I would say something to bring, if possible, some People amongst us to be a little better acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with themselves.</item>
               <item>2. I would offer a few Considerations for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the fear of the <hi>LORD,</hi> or sincere Religion amongst us.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. There is a sort of People among us, whom I would fain, might it please God, bring a little better acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with themselves, than they yet seem to be. Those I mean, who are observed almost every-where to set up the loudest cry for <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Religion as by Law therein established;</hi> whilst yet they seem most industrious by their notorious <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries,</hi> and <hi>Lawless</hi> Lives to provide, that no <hi>sober</hi> Man that knows them, should ever in the least suspect, that they have any fear of God before their eyes.</p>
            <p>Now I do most earnestly beseech these Men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider a little, both what they are, and what Mischiefs they are a doing daily, even to that <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> whatever they mean by these Names, which they would be thought so much to honour.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whilst they keep such a stir about the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Religion by Law established;</hi> and in the mean time so quite forget <hi>God,</hi> as tho' none of all these had any relation at all to him: Yea, whilst they are wont to laugh at the serious naming of God, as a <hi>Cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or piece of <hi>Phanaticism,</hi> and hardly ever name him themselves, unless in some horrid <hi>Oath,</hi> or direful <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:135236:15"/>as often on <hi>themselves</hi> as any others: In a word, whilst they make a sport of <hi>sin</hi> in <hi>themselves,</hi> and of <hi>Religion</hi> in <hi>others;</hi> as the <hi>Philosopher</hi> in <hi>Hierocles,</hi> said to a wicked Wretch in the same Ship with him, when being in some danger he began to pray, <hi>Hold thy peace, Friend, least the Gods should hear thee, and know that we have such a Fellow in our Company:</hi> So <hi>are their King,</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> (whoever they be) greatly concern'd to beg of these their Friends, as they love them, to hold their Peace, least the World should know that they have any such Friends as they: Whose very professing themselves their Friends, is to do the very worst thing they can, both to disgrace them, and to tempt their Enemies to think much the better of themselves for being Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to them, whose <hi>Friends</hi> are so much the <hi>Enemies</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and serious <hi>Piety.</hi> The case of a <hi>Kingdom</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed lamentable, when Men are thus tempted to think, that there can be no <hi>Piety</hi> in the <hi>Loyal,</hi> or no <hi>Loyalty</hi> in the <hi>Pious,</hi> as tho' <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> were the <hi>Two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> which no Man can serve at once. And some will be thus tempted, who whilst they can on the one hand spie out for themselves <hi>Leaders</hi> or <hi>Companions</hi> who seem to follow <hi>God;</hi> and on the other hand can see many (thô God be thank'd, far from all) seemingly very zealous for the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> and yet as impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Enemies to sincere <hi>Piety</hi> in their <hi>Lives,</hi> as in their <hi>Words</hi> to <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisie,</hi> will be apt to think themselves nearest <hi>God,</hi> when farthest from both the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> which such Men honour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such good <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Church-of England-Men</hi> are they who live not in the fear of <hi>God,</hi> that the whole business of their Lives is nothing else, but a continual provoking of Almighty God to pour down his most dreadful <hi>Judgments</hi> on the whole <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Tell me,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135236:16"/>
               <hi>Sirs,</hi> I beseech you, do you think your <hi>sins</hi> no <hi>provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi> Or can you hope, that <hi>God,</hi> thô daily <hi>provoked</hi> will never <hi>visit?</hi> He that affirms either of these, will be found at the bottom little better than an <hi>Atheist,</hi> and then none but he can think a <hi>wicked Man</hi> can be <hi>Loyal.</hi> Nay, thô <q>you were able to brag of the brave Exploits you have done in their Service, thô you be not of the inferiour gang, who only use to whet their Tongues like a Sword, and bend their Bows to shoot their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, bitter words, at random; but of those who have sometimes with good success managed either the <hi>Sword</hi> or the <hi>Pen</hi> in their cause: Yet alas, what does all this come to? for where either your <hi>Learning</hi> or your <hi>Valour</hi> hath taken off one, your <hi>wicked Lives</hi> have made them twenty Enemies. You have, it may be, sometimes confuted or defeated for them two or three weak Mortals, and have been arming <hi>Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> all your Life long against them.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. You wage a continual War and Rebellion against them both underhand, and <hi>Judas</hi>-like, betray them with a <hi>kiss.</hi> You live in a constant disobedience to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the one, and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the other, whom in words you honour. Suppose we were all come (which God forbid) to that heighth of <hi>Irreligion,</hi> as with the <hi>Hobbist</hi> to account the Gospel of Christ,
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.5.</note>
               <hi>Who is the Prince of the Kings of the earth,</hi> to be no <hi>Law</hi> to any People, till it have received the <hi>Civil Sanction;</hi> yet certainly in this Kingdom, where <hi>Christian Religion</hi> is by Law establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to live <hi>wickedly,</hi> is to live <hi>disloyally,</hi> and he that by so doing lists himself among the Enemies of both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> has no body to blame for it, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, if others so account of him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Into what intolerable straits do these evil Livers drive both the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> by their so much
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135236:16"/>seeming Zeal for them? Which way soever they shall turn themselves, to this pass they are brought, that they must needs disoblige great numbers of the People. Either they must very severely chastise these <hi>good Friends</hi> of theirs for their wickedness, as their own Laws require them to do, and so be sure to lose them; or they must against their Duty connive at their sins, and so lose many better Men than they. Either these zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Friends</hi> of theirs must be made to suffer by the <hi>Sword of Justice</hi> and <hi>Rod of Discipline,</hi> or the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> must expose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the <hi>wrath</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>reproach</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> by suffering for their sakes the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> to be trampled on with impunity. Now what can be more <hi>displeasing</hi> to a <hi>good King</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> or indeed more <hi>pernicious</hi> to <hi>any,</hi> than to be always exercising nothing but severity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Lastly, The <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have now long been stiled, <hi>Defenders of the Faith,</hi> and now, if ever (blessed be God) we have <hi>Princes</hi> whom it can be no <hi>flattery</hi> to call so: And the <hi>good Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> is this, <hi>That Justice may be minister'd indifferently, to the punishment of wickedness and vice, and the maintenance of true Religion and Vertue:</hi> This, I say, is the very hearty <hi>Prayer</hi> of every <hi>Loyal Subject</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> And now <hi>Sirs,</hi> cannot you thus <hi>pray?</hi> Then I beseech you, what have you to do with <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and the <hi>Church of England?</hi> Can you thus pray indeed? Then can you no longer live <hi>wickedly,</hi> except you can find in your hearts to pray for your own <hi>punishment.</hi> In short, to live <hi>irreligiously,</hi> and yet pretend to <hi>Loyalty,</hi> is in effect, to wish the King's Title of <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into this, <hi>Protector of the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O when will Men awake and come to themselves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135236:17"/>When will we begin to call to mind what we are? or what we should be? When will we begin to act with so much reason, as that the very <hi>Atheist</hi> himself (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the absurdest Fool upon Earth) may not justly laugh at us for our folly, in saying, We <hi>believe in God,</hi> whilst we <hi>fear him not,</hi> in professing ourselves <hi>Christians,</hi> whilst we live most <hi>unchristianly,</hi> in boasting of our <hi>Loyalty,</hi> whilst we break all good <hi>Laws,</hi> finally in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be very zealous for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> whilst we <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>oppose</hi> nothing more than a <hi>seasonable Reformation.</hi> Whilst we continue to live and act at this mad rate, must not all that observe it conclude, either that <hi>we</hi> are no <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> or <hi>Protestants</hi> are no <hi>Christians,</hi> or <hi>Christians</hi> are <hi>Mad-men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Blessed God! that in this Age of the <hi>World,</hi> and of <hi>Christianity;</hi> yea, that in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> so long blessed above most other parts of the <hi>Christian</hi> World, with the brightest Sun-shine of the <hi>Gospel</hi> of Christ, and with the cherishing light of God's <hi>Countenance</hi> too; a <hi>Kingdom</hi> which hath <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgments</hi> so righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, as are the <hi>Laws</hi> of this wisely constituted <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>hath God so nigh unto it, as the LORD our God hath ever been unto us, in all things that we have call'd upon him for;</hi> and of which therefore one might well think, that all who hear of it should say, as once of <hi>Israel, Surely this great Nation is a wise and understanding People:</hi> That even <hi>Here,</hi> and <hi>Now,</hi> there should be found among <hi>Ʋs</hi> Men, either so <hi>brutishly ignorant,</hi> as not to know, <hi>That the</hi> All-disposing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence <hi>of</hi> God <hi>ordereth all the affairs of this inferiour World;</hi> or so <hi>childishly inadvertent,</hi> as not to observe <hi>the most distinguishing</hi> Characters <hi>of his</hi> special <hi>favour, legible in his gracious Dispensations towards us:</hi> Or,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135236:17"/>what's worse still, so <hi>desperately mad,</hi> as to despise the <hi>plainest and most earnest Commands of the blessed</hi> Jesus: That <hi>we</hi> should any of us at <hi>this</hi> day seem so insensible what it is, either to be <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Brethren,</hi> or <hi>Christians,</hi> so altogether forgetful of <hi>ourselves,</hi> so quite worn out of <hi>kind,</hi> and out of all <hi>Religion</hi> too; that neither the sence of our total <hi>dependence</hi> upon God as <hi>Men,</hi> nor the sensible benefits of <hi>Civil Government</hi> as <hi>Citizens,</hi> nor yet the inestimable Priviledges and Advantages of a most holy <hi>Religion,</hi> as <hi>Christians;</hi> that neither our own <hi>present safety</hi> and <hi>future happiness,</hi> nor the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> the Peace and Prosperity of our <hi>Country,</hi> and <hi>Posterity,</hi> nor yet the <hi>Honour</hi> of our blessed <hi>Jesus,</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>His,</hi> that is, the <hi>Protestant Interest</hi> in the World: That nothing of all this should even <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain</hi> us to do the Duties of the Text, without any <hi>Monitor,</hi> but that in every Man's breast, is, I must needs say, to me a very astonishing thing: and yet, alas, so sadly true, that as one cannot but both <hi>blush</hi> and <hi>tremble</hi> to think of it, so is it a very strong temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to cease forever from perswading Men to things which they seem so fully <hi>resolved</hi> against, that they are impatient so much as to hear of them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But I hope far better things of all <hi>You,</hi> who have the patience to hear me this day. And therefore with some confidence of prevailing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would now offer a few things to Consideration, for the promoting of the <hi>fear of the LORD,</hi> or <hi>sincere Religion</hi> among us. Let me most earnestly beseech <hi>You</hi> all, by all that <hi>You</hi> can think dear unto <hi>You,</hi> to labour every one, according to his <hi>ability, station,</hi> and <hi>oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities,</hi> to revive the fear of the <hi>LORD</hi> in the Land, and so to <hi>save your selves from this untoward Generation.</hi> Till this great Lesson be well learn'd, 'tis in vain to take
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135236:18"/>in another; and indeed, he that has learn'd this, will soon learn all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sincere Piety</hi> being once become the natural temper of our renewed hearts, our <hi>gracious Princes</hi> may be well assured of our <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and <hi>We</hi> of <hi>God's Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> under Their <hi>Government.</hi> But, whilst there is so much <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>bare-faced Impiety,</hi> or so much <hi>slie</hi> and <hi>mask'd Hypocrisie;</hi> whilst Men dare so <hi>openly</hi> rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the great <hi>King of kings,</hi> or under some plausible Disguizes <hi>secretly</hi> undermine his <hi>Government;</hi> either so <hi>impudently</hi> trample his holy <hi>Laws</hi> under foot, or so <hi>treacherously</hi> cloak their Villanies under a seeming <hi>Zeal</hi> for them; what can we expect, but that God should sooner or later <hi>arise</hi> and <hi>visit for these things,</hi> and by vindicating his Divine <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Omniscience</hi> at once, make us feel in earnest, what it is to defie <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence,</hi> and endeavour foolishly to <hi>mock</hi> Him, from whom no Secrets can be hid. To move us the more effectually to the <hi>fear of the LORD,</hi> it may be, I hope, enough at this time, to call to mind but a few things, which one would think we should none of us easily forget.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How long hath our <hi>good God</hi> already waited to be gracious to us? And how doth He even yet, after we have so <hi>often,</hi> so <hi>long,</hi> and so <hi>highly</hi> provoked him, not only by the most wonderful <hi>long-suffering,</hi> and <hi>forbearance,</hi> allow us time enough to consider, and grow wiser for ourselves; but by such <hi>extraordinary Deliverances,</hi> and <hi>signal Mercies</hi> as the whole Christian World seems amazed at, <hi>invite,</hi> nay <hi>hire</hi> us to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py? Will we yet go on to <hi>despise the riches of his goodness?</hi> O then, for shame, never open a mouth to complain any more, thô Wrath should come upon us to the uttermost.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:135236:18"/> 2. How cried we out but a-while ago, for our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> as thô we did not think our very <hi>Lives</hi> worth the saving, without the <hi>Liberty</hi> of serving God as we ought, and doing Justice. It hath now pleased God, (blessed for ever be his <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness!</hi>) by a most <hi>seasonable Providence</hi> to rid us of these fears, and to put us into such a Condition, as we may now safely <hi>fear</hi> both <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> and need not be <hi>afraid</hi> of either of them for doing so. We may do our whole Duty to <hi>God,</hi> and need not be afraid of the <hi>King</hi> for <hi>that.</hi> We may do even all that the <hi>King</hi> desires of us, and not be afraid of <hi>God</hi> for <hi>that.</hi> God hath blessed us with <hi>Princes,</hi> who seem to make <hi>Religion</hi> their <hi>special Care,</hi> even as they Themselves seem to be the <hi>special Care of Heaven.</hi> God hath blessed us with <hi>Judges,</hi> who are Men of <hi>tried Integrity,</hi> and such as in the worst of Times have shew'd themselves <hi>Temptation-proof,</hi> fearing God too much, to be either <hi>frown'd</hi> or <hi>brib'd</hi> out of <hi>Justice;</hi> and too faithful to the <hi>Government,</hi> to sacrifice the <hi>good Laws</hi> thereof, either to their <hi>fears</hi> or <hi>hopes.</hi> God hath bless'd us with <hi>Magistrates</hi> on the <hi>Bench,</hi> who, I hope, were born for a time of <hi>Reformation,</hi> to grace <hi>Religion,</hi> to bring the <hi>fear of God</hi> into <hi>fashion</hi> again, and to look <hi>Prophaneness</hi> and <hi>Debauchery</hi> out of Countenance: and who will own it a part of the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s Character, <hi>to fear the LORD, to serve his</hi> King <hi>and his</hi> Country, <hi>and to influence the Neighbourhood into all manner of</hi> Piety, Justice, <hi>and</hi> Sobriety <hi>by his own</hi> Example: Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, who have Souls too <hi>generous</hi> and <hi>brave,</hi> either to be daunted by the <hi>Rants</hi> and <hi>Scoulings</hi> of the <hi>Great</hi> Ones, or to be at all moved either with the <hi>Cursings</hi> or <hi>Flatteries</hi> of the <hi>lower</hi> Form of Sinners. If <hi>God</hi> have not pleas'd us now, when can we be pleas'd? If
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135236:19"/>He have not now obliged us to fear Him, when will we become sensible of any Obligation?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why should not the <hi>present Government</hi> under which we live be very easie and pleasing to us, if it be not for this one reason, that it seems to draw too near to a <hi>Theocracy.</hi> We fear'd <hi>Man,</hi> and were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to indure it. This <hi>Government</hi> seems to require nothing more of us, but to fear <hi>God,</hi> and we can much less indure that. We were weary of the very <hi>thoughts</hi> of an <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> and shall we now shew ourselves as impatient of a <hi>Legal</hi> One, and only through our hatred of the only thing it seems to threaten us withal, a <hi>seasonable Reformation?</hi> If this be indeed our temper, 'tis too plain we have not yet smarted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and therefore have cause to fear a sharper <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stisement</hi> yet. Had God left us but for a <hi>while</hi> to <hi>feel</hi> all the Evils we were <hi>afraid of,</hi> we would have been very <hi>proud of,</hi> and mightily <hi>obliged</hi> by the least of those Blessings we now so unthankfully enjoy. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more of the sharp <hi>Goad</hi> might have made us more tractable to an easie <hi>Yoke.</hi> But thus it often is, both our <hi>good God,</hi> and the <hi>best of Kings</hi> want their due Honour from us, because we have not had those over us who have been <hi>Tyrants</hi> enough to scourge us into Duty. If God's heavy hand had <hi>bruis'd</hi> us enough, possibly we should now begin both to <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>love</hi> him, when he is beginning to <hi>heal</hi> us.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="4">4. If we walk not now in <hi>the fear of the LORD,</hi> we proclaim to the wide World, that we most basely <hi>dissembled,</hi> when we seem'd afraid to lose the Free Exercise of our <hi>holy Religion,</hi> and all the benefits of <hi>good Laws,</hi> and a <hi>Legal Government.</hi> We plainly shew, that the thing we most fear'd was, lest some should make so bold with our <hi>Estates,</hi> as to abridge our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135236:19"/>Lusts and Vanities of their too plentiful allowance, and not leave us room enough <hi>to make provision for the flesh, to fulfil the lusts thereof.</hi> We were afraid least our <hi>Riot</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> should lose the <hi>liberty</hi> of devouring all, and least our <hi>Vices</hi> should be as meanly fed, as those <hi>poor People</hi> usually are, whom we rack and squeeze to maintain them. No doubt at all of it, but many of us fear'd <hi>Slavery,</hi> and for that <hi>Popery</hi> too; but certainly <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> could never be much in their thoughts, who are now so busie to make it known, that they fear nothing so much as to be <hi>reformed,</hi> and tied up by the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> to live <hi>godly, righteously, and soberly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Lastly, Will you give me leave to add this one thing more? The <hi>Fear of the LORD</hi> will preserve these <hi>Kingdoms</hi> in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> which nothing else can long do, and that at so easie a rate, that no Man needs complain he is burden'd with the Charges of doing it.</p>
               <p>For, besides that the <hi>Fear of the LORD,</hi> and it alone can assure us of <hi>God's Protection</hi> and <hi>Blessing,</hi> which is the only thing can make our <hi>Wars</hi> short and prosperous, and our <hi>Peace</hi> durable and happy; it will moreover do all this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It will abate and cool our mutual <hi>Heats</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimosities,</hi> close up our <hi>Breaches</hi> and <hi>Divisions,</hi> end our <hi>Contentions,</hi> silence our <hi>Murmurings,</hi> enlarge our Hearts for <hi>Publick Concerns,</hi> make <hi>Private Interests</hi> give place to the <hi>Common Good,</hi> and <hi>unite</hi> us all, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever differing in small things, in the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>Country,</hi> and of <hi>one another:</hi> So shall we be too <hi>good</hi> to find a <hi>Traytor</hi> at home, and too <hi>strong</hi> to fear an <hi>Enemy</hi> abroad.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:135236:20"/> 2. It makes all <hi>Officers</hi> faithful in their <hi>Trusts,</hi> and regardful of their <hi>Oaths</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> which they are sworn to act by; so that amongst the rest, all <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners</hi> and <hi>Assessors</hi> take great care that the <hi>King</hi> want no part of what the Nation gives him for its own preservation, and that no Man by their negligence be encouraged to use a <hi>bad Conscience,</hi> whilst he finds he needs not pay half so much for it, and yet be as safe, as they who are made to pay double for using a good one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It teacheth <hi>Men of Estates</hi> to live <hi>frugally,</hi> to <hi>moderate</hi> their Expences, and to <hi>spare</hi> Superfluities; so that the poor <hi>Tenant</hi> is not made first to labour hard to pay his <hi>Landlord's Rent,</hi> and next to famish when he has done to pay his <hi>Taxes</hi> too. The <hi>Poor</hi> is not left to be the burden of the <hi>Poor</hi> only, nor by wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring abroad to reproach the <hi>Government.</hi> 'Tis thought a very easie bargain to pay but a Man's <hi>Luxury</hi> and <hi>Vanity,</hi> for his own and his <hi>Country's Safety,</hi> or to make such a Purchase at no dearer rate than that of <hi>living soberly,</hi> and not casting the Childrens Bread to <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Swine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. It makes it thought <hi>good Husbandry,</hi> as well as <hi>Christianity</hi> to cast into the <hi>Publick Treasury</hi> for a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's Safety,</hi> at least all that which either <hi>malice, spite,</hi> and <hi>revenge,</hi> or a <hi>proud, stomachful, and litigious</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, now buries so freely without any hopes of a resurrection, in the <hi>Lawyer's Pockets.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>And now I shall not need to tell you, <hi>My Honourable Lord,</hi> and <hi>Worshipful Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Magistracy,</hi> how much it lieth upon you, to endeavour that God may have his due fear and honour, without which you can never expect your own. You act for God as <hi>his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters for good</hi> to us. <hi>You judge not for man, but for the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135236:20"/>LORD, who is with you in the Judgment. Therefore let the fear of God be upon you, and take heed what ye do.</hi> It will, I know, be your care to see, as well as you can, that all the <hi>good Laws</hi> in force against all <hi>Wickedness</hi> and <hi>Immorality,</hi> of what sort soever, may have a more vigorous <hi>Execution</hi> among us. Their <hi>Majesties</hi> have shewn their pious Care, in causing some of these to be sent Re-printed unto us; and we, according to our Duty, have both <hi>read</hi> them as the <hi>Laws of the Land,</hi> and <hi>preach'd</hi> them as the <hi>Laws of God,</hi> to the People in our Churches. But yet after all, there wants some easier way of executing them by <hi>inferiour Officers,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which they will lie in many places useless and dead. Having given you this, I hope, no unseasonable hint, to all the rest I have but a word.</p>
            <p>
               <q>They say, that in <hi>Aethiopia</hi> the <hi>Judges</hi> were wont to sit on lower Benches, leaving above them twelve empty Chairs, which they call'd the Seats of the <hi>Angels,</hi> insisibly presiding in those <hi>Courts.</hi>
               </q> Let me now beseech all those who have any business in these Places of <hi>Judicature,</hi> to consider that they come there into the presence not of <hi>Men</hi> only, but of the great Judge of all Men, <hi>who standeth in the Congregation of the mighty, and judgeth among the Gods:</hi> and to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves as becometh Men in such a <hi>Presence,</hi> with fear and trembling. And whether you be <hi>Plantiff, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, Accuser, Witness, Juror, or Pleader,</hi> take the <hi>Roman Orator's</hi> Advice, <hi>Remember that you have God your witness; that is, your own Conscience; than which, God himself hath given nothing more divine to Men.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you do, both the Witness and the Judge are present, and there is no escaping.</p>
            <p>Let then the <hi>fear of God</hi> prevail above all, so shall both <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Justices</hi> be much eas'd of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135236:21"/>both in these Courts, and in their own private Houses. Then will the <hi>Government</hi> be secure, and the <hi>Nation</hi> happy, when Mens own <hi>Consciences</hi> begin to keep them in awe, and they are ashamed to feel their own <hi>hearts reproach them,</hi> when they have learn'd to stand more in awe of <hi>God,</hi> and of his <hi>Vicegerent</hi> in their own Breasts, than of any <hi>Power</hi> on Earth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever; when they cannot hope, they themselves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judges, to escape the severest Sentence for any dishonour done either to <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>King,</hi> for any, either <hi>Impiety</hi> or <hi>Injustice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May the great and good God vouchsafe unto us all his Grace and Holy Spirit, and keep us in his Faith, Fear, and Love, through <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> our <hi>Lord,</hi> to whom with the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> One <hi>God</hi> blessed for ever, be all Honour and Glory, and Praise, now, and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135236:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>